Guide to the Virginians for Dulles records, 1947-1984
George Mason University Libraries
- Series 2: Court Proceedings, 1966-1983; (11.5 boxes)
  - Virginians for Dulles v. John Volpe: Pretrial - Documents to Be Introduced as Evidence by Airline Defendants, 1958-1972 (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Virginians for Dulles v. John Volpe: Pretrial Statement and Preliminary Statement of Plaintiff, 1971-1972 (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Virginians for Dulles v. John Volpe: Pretrial Statement of Government Defendants, 1970-1972 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Virginians for Dulles v. John Volpe: Pretrial Statement of Airline Defendants, April 7, 1972 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Virginians for Dulles v. John Volpe: Res Judicata - Defendants' Motion for Res Judicata and Summary Judgment, April-May 1973 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Virginians for Dulles v. John Volpe: Res Judicata - Plantiff's Memorandum in Response to Defendants' Motion to Dismiss as Res Judicata, May 29, 1973 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Virginians for Dulles v. John Volpe: Service Records, Correspondence, and Memoranda, 1970-1971 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Virginians for Dulles v. John Volpe: Stipulation of Facts and Revised Stipulation, ca 1971-1972 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Virginians for Dulles v. John Volpe: Subpoenas, April-May 1972 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Virginians for Dulles v. John Volpe: Testimony - Airline Defendant Affidavits, April-May 1972 (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Virginians for Dulles v. John Volpe: Testimony - Defense Expert Reports, ca. 1971-1972 (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Virginians for Dulles v. John Volpe: Testimony - Expert Witness Resumes, 1971-1972 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Virginians for Dulles v. John Volpe: Testimony - Miscellaneous Documents, Correspondence, Reports, 1966-1972 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Virginians for Dulles v. John Volpe: Testimony - Plaintiff Expert and Citizen Testimony, ca. 1971-1972 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Virginians for Dulles v. John Volpe: Testimony - Plaintiff Expert Correspondence, 1971-1972 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Virginians for Dulles v. John Volpe: Testimony - Plaintiff Expert Witness on Air and Noise Pollution, 1967-1972 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Virginians for Dulles v. John Volpe: Testimony - Plaintiff Expert Witness on Air and Noise Pollution, extra copies, 1970-1972 (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Virginians for Dulles v. John Volpe: Testimony - Plaintiff Lay Witness Affidavits, extra copies, pt 1, 1971-1972 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Virginians for Dulles v. John Volpe: Testimony - Plaintiff Lay Witness Affidavits, extra copies, pt 2, 1971-1972 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Virginians for Dulles v. John Volpe: Testimony - Plaintiff Lay Witness Correspondence and Memoranda, 1971-1972 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Virginians for Dulles v. John Volpe: Transcript of Court Proceedings, July 1971 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Virginians for Dulles v. John Volpe: Transcript of Court Proceedings, Court Draft, Vol. III, May 10, 1972 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Virginians for Dulles v. John Volpe: Trial Notes, ca. 1970-1972 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Virginians for Dulles v. John Volpe: Trial Transcripts, May 11, 1972 (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Virginians for Dulles v. John Volpe: Witness Files - Bacon, Beckleman, Briggs, Bristol, Copley, ca. 1971-1972 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Virginians for Dulles v. John Volpe: Witness Files - Gerarde, ca. 1971-1972 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Virginians for Dulles v. John Volpe: Witness Files - Goldwater, ca. 1971-1972 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Virginians for Dulles v. John Volpe: Witness Files - Guerrant, Kolk, Linn, ca. 1971-1972 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Virginians for Dulles v. John Volpe: Witness Files - Glorig, ca. 1971-1972 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Virginians for Dulles v. John Volpe: Witness Files - Madsen, Melugin, Mohler, ca. 1971-1972 (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Virginians for Dulles v. John Volpe: Witness Files - Newill, ca. 1971-1972 (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Virginians for Dulles v. John Volpe: Witness Files - Pendley, Powers, Press, ca. 1971-1972 (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - Virginians for Dulles v. John Volpe: Witness Files - Russel, Saunders, ca. 1971-1972 (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - Virginians for Dulles v. John Volpe: Witness Files - Sellman, Shaffer, ca. 1971-1972 (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - Virginians for Dulles v. John Volpe: Witness Files - Smith, Sperry, Swanson, ca. 1971-1972 (Box 19, Folder 11)
  - Virginians for Dulles v. John Volpe: Witness Files - Westfield, Wilding, ca. 1971-1972 (Box 19, Folder 12)
- Series 3: Legal Reference, 1947-1983; (3 boxes)
  This series contains notes, correspondence, and supplementary reference materials gathered by Virginians for Dulles board members and their lawyers to support litigation strategies against Washington National Airport and the FAA. Whereas the materials in Series 2 pertain either to civil cases directly involving Virginians for Dulles or to cases initiated by other plaintiffs in the same timeframe and geographic locale, the materials in Series 3 consist largely of facsimilies of older cases decided by precedents considered by VFD lawyers as prospective bases of litigation during the early 1980s. In addition to copies of cases, this series includes correspondence and notes referring to prior VFD litigation against Washington National Airport.
  - Copies of Cases Re: Actions Constituting a Taking, pt 1, 1956-1977 (Box 19, Folder 13)
  - Copies of Cases Re: Actions Constituting a Taking, pt 2, 1961-1971 (Box 19, Folder 14)
  - Copies of Cases Re: Antitrust Law, pt 1, 1950-1980 (Box 19, Folder 15)
  - Copies of Cases, Re: Antitrust Law, pt 2, 1972-1982 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Copies of Cases, Re: Antitrust Law, pt 3, 1947-1983 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Copies of Cases Re: Eminent Domain, pt 1, 1953-1965 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Copies of Cases Re: Eminent Domain, pt 2, 1958-1965 (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Copies of Cases Re: Eminent Domain, pt 3, 1968-1983 (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Copies of Cases Re: FAA Responsibility in Airport Planning, 1950-1959 (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Copies of Cases Re: Municipal Ordinances, Preemption, State Laws, 1953-1982 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Copies of Cases Re: Nuisance, Violation of Regulations, 1956-1979 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Copies of Cases Re: Statute of Limitations, 1958-1976 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence and Legal Precedence: Costello v. United States, Joseph v. Helms, etc., 1979-1983 (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - Index Cards Re: National Airport Suit [Virginians for Dulles v. Volpe], 1970-1971 (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Luedtke v. County of Milwaukee: Notes and Newsclippings, 1975 (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - Notes and Legal Precedence, pt 1, 1970-1971 (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Notes and Legal Precedence, pt 2, 1970-1972 (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - Notes on Aircraft Noise, pt 1, ca. 1969-1971 (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - Notes on Aircraft Noise, pt 2, 1970-1972 (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - Notes on National Airport Litigation, 1982-1983 (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - Notes on Primary Jurisdiction, undated (Box 22, Folder 6)
- Series 4: Reports and Comments, 1966-1983; (12 boxes)
  This series contains reports on airport policies and procedures; informational pamphlets; detailed studies on aircraft noise and emmissions; comments by Virginians for Dulles and others on FAA policy proposals; and transcripts of hearings before the Civil Aeronautics Board and the Aviation Subcommittee of the US House Committee on Public Works and Transportation. Prominent documents in this series include several draft environmental impact statements (DEIS) and policy proposals for Washington National and Dulles International Airports prepared by the FAA and published by the United States Department of Transportation, as well as dozens of comments on these reports by Virginians for Dulles and other citizens action groups.
  - Air Pollution Abatement Activity and Report on DC Air Quality Control, 1966-1968 (Box 22, Folder 7)
  - Air Pollution: Aircraft Emmissions Reports, 1971-1972 (Box 22, Folder 8)
  - Air Pollution: Miscellaneous Facts and Reports, pt 1, 1967-1970 (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - Air Pollution: Miscellaneous Facts and Reports, pt 2, 1969-1971 (Box 23, Folder 2)
  - Arbitration as an Alternative to Regulation... the National Airport Noise Problem, 1982 (Box 23, Folder 3)
  - Assessment of Airport Emmission Control Technology, September 1971 (Box 23, Folder 4)
  - Civil Aeronautics Board: Brief of Concerned Citizens, the Palisades Citizens Association and Committe Against National; Joint Petition to Intervene, 1968-1970 (Box 23, Folder 5)
  - Civil Aeronautics Board (CAB): Reports and Investigations by the CAB's Airline Scheduling Committee, pt 1, 1980-1981 (Box 24, Folder 1)
    Washington National flight schedules and antitrust immunity
  - Civil Aeronautics Board (CAB): Reports and Investigations by the CAB's Airline Scheduling Committee, pt 2, 1982-1983 (Box 24, Folder 2)
  - Comments of Virginians for Dulles to the Federal Aviation Administration (FAA), March 1973 (Box 24, Folder 3)
  - Conceptual Framework for Trade-Off Analysis of Multiple Airport Operation: Case Study of the Metropolitan Washington Airports, 1978 (Box 24, Folder 4)
    dissertation
  - DC-9 Airplane Characteristics for Airport Planning, September 1968 (Box 24, Folder 5)
  - DC-10 Airplane Characteristics for Airport Planning, December 1971 (Box 24, Folder 6)
  - Dulles Airport: Direct Economic Impact of Dulles Airport, September 1977 (Box 24, Folder 7)
  - Dulles Airport: Environmental Impact Assessment, September 1977 (Box 25, Folder 1)
  - Dulles Airport: Industrial Area Plan, September 1977 (Box 25, Folder 2)
  - Eastern Airlines: Flight Manual Facsimilies, 1967-1971 (Box 25, Folder 3)
  - Environmental Impact Statement: Comments on EIS draft, pt 1, 1973 (Box 25, Folder 4)
  - Environmental Impact Statement: Comments on EIS draft, pt 2, 1978 (Box 25, Folder 5)
  - Environmental Impact Statement: Comments on EIS draft, pt 3, 1978 (Box 25, Folder 6)
  - Environmental Impact Statement: Comments on EIS draft, pt 4, 1978 (Box 25, Folder 7)
  - Environmental Impact Statement: Comments on EIS draft, pt 5, 1978-1980 (Box 26, Folder 1)
  - Environmental Impact Statement: Comments on EIS draft, pt 6, 1980 (Box 26, Folder 2)
  - Environmental Impact Statement: Correspondence re: EIS draft, 1977-1978 (Box 26, Folder 3)
  - Environmental Impact Statement: Draft, February 1983 (Box 26, Folder 4)
  - Environmental Impact Statement: Draft, March 1973 (Box 26, Folder 5)
  - Environmental Impact Statement: Draft Appendix, March 1978 (Box 26, Folder 6)
  - Environmental Impact Statement: Draft with Annotations, March 1978 (Box 27, Folder 1)
  - Environmental Impact Statement: Final Draft, November 1980 (Box 27, Folder 2)
  - Environmental Impact Statement: Outline and Preliminary Analysis of Existing Airport Policy, August-November 1977 (Box 27, Folder 3)
  - FAA Publications: Guide to FAA Publications, Transportation Noise Bibliography, Energy Primer, Newsleteter, and Press Release, 1974-1980 (Box 27, Folder 4)
  - Federal Register re: FAA Airport Regulations, 1975-1976 (Box 27, Folder 5)
  - Joint Air Transportation Demand-Capacity Study of the Baltimore-Washington Bi-Region, December 1968 (Box 27, Folder 6)
  - Metropolitan Washington Airport Policies: Consumer and Environmental Effects, Final Report, October 1976 (Box 28, Folder 1)
    Federal Aviation Administration (FAA)
  - Metropolitan Washington Airport Policy Analysis: Air Traffic Delays, September 1976 (Box 28, Folder 2)
  - Metropolitan Washington Airport Policy Analysis: Airport Investment Policy Requirements, September 1976 (Box 28, Folder 3)
  - Metropolitan Washington Airport Policy Analysis: Wide-Body Aircraft Demand Potential, September 1976 (Box 28, Folder 4)
  - Metropolitan Washington Airport Policy: Comments and Public Hearings, pt 1, 1976-1980 (Box 28, Folder 5)
  - Metropolitan Washington Airport Policy: Comments and Public Hearings, pt 2, 1980 (Box 28, Folder 6)
  - Metropolitan Washington Airport Policy: High Density Airport Slot Allocation, 1976-1983 (Box 28, Folder 7)
  - Metropolitan Washington Airport Policy: Preliminary Regulatory Evaluation, August 1981 (Box 28, Folder 8)
  - National Air Carrier Association: Comments on Airport Slot Allocation Report, 1980 (Box 28, Folder 9)
  - National Environmental Policy Act of 1969 and FAA Proposals for Airport Envirnomental Policy, pt 1, 1970-1973 (Box 29, Folder 1)
  - National Environmental Policy Act of 1969 and FAA Proposals for Airport Envirnomental Policy, pt 2, 1971-1975 (Box 29, Folder 2)
  - Noise: Analysis of Quiet Engine Retrofit Program; Noise Exposure Contours; Human Response to Sonic Booms, 1970-1971 (Box 29, Folder 3)
  - Noise and Health: Psychosociological Response to the Mean Level of Environmental Stimulation; Effects of Noise on Health in the Residential Urban Environment; Noise: A Health Problem, 1964-1978 (Box 29, Folder 4)
  - Noise Annoyance in Central London, March 1966 (Box 29, Folder 5)
  - Noise: Aviation Noise Abatement Policy; FAA Press Releases, 1974-1976 (Box 29, Folder 6)
  - Noise: Estimated Airplane Noise Levels; Environmental Protection Agency Notice of Proposed Rulemaking on Noise Levels, August 2, 1976 (Box 29, Folder 7)
  - Noise Exposure Forecasts and Noise Control, 1972-1976 (Box 30, Folder 1)
  - Noise Impact of Washington National Airport, 1977-1980 (Box 30, Folder 2)
  - Noise: Legal Aspects of Airport Noise and Sonic Boom; Conference on STOL Airport Noise Certification, 1969 (Box 30, Folder 3)
  - Noise: Proposed National Strategy for Noise Abatement and Control, Draft; Guidelines for Considering Noise in Land-Use Planning and Control; Comments of CWPS on FAA Proposed Regulations on Airport Noise, 1967-1980 (Box 30, Folder 4)
    Environmental Protection Agency, Federal Interagency Committee on Urban Noise, Council on Wage and Price Stability
  - Noise: Sound Without Value; Aircraft Noise Measurements Near Washington National Airport; Generation and Control of Aircraft Noise and Sonic Booms, 1967-1971 (Box 30, Folder 5)
  - Noise: Statement of the Air Line Pilots Association; Statements Presented to the Aviation Committee of the US Senate Committee on Commerce, 1971 (Box 30, Folder 6)
  - Noise: Transportation Noise Bulletin, October 1971 (Box 31, Folder 1)
  - Notes and Comments on the Bolfing Report and Kling Report, 1970 (Box 31, Folder 2)
  - Plan for the Implementation of Ambient Air Quality Standards in Maryland, pt 1, 1971 (Box 31, Folder 3)
    Maryland State Department of Health and Mental Hygiene
  - Plan for the Implementation of Ambient Air Quality Standards in Maryland, pt 2; Final Report of Maryland Citizen Committee to Draft Environmental Ordinance, November 1970 (Box 31, Folder 4)
  - Planning: Growth and Use of Washington Area Airports; The Washington-Baltimore Area Airports; Airport Resource Allocation in the Washington Metropolitan Area, 1970-1971 (Box 31, Folder 5)
  - Safety: Air Traffic Control, January 21, 1982 (Box 31, Folder 6)
  - Safety: Aircraft Accident Report, January 13, 1982 (Box 32, Folder 1)
    National Transportation Safety Board
  - Safety at Washington National Airport, 1972-1983 (Box 32, Folder 2)
    Virginians for Dulles, FAA, Aviation Consumer Action Project (ACAP)
  - Safety: Building Regulations, 1980-1983 (Box 32, Folder 3)
    Air Traffic Control Association; FAA; Air Line Pilots Association; National Transportation Safety Board
  - Statements on Washington National Airport, 1969-1972 (Box 32, Folder 4)
  - Washington-Baltimore Airport Investigation: Civil Aeronautics Board Staff Report and Statements, 1969 (Box 32, Folder 5)
  - Washington National Airport: A Special Study; Washington National Airport Noise Analysis, 1969; 1977 (Box 32, Folder 6)
    Arlington County Chamber of Commerce
  - Washington National Airport Facilities Planning Guide, July 22, 1982 (Box 33, Folder 1)
  - Washington National Airport Facilities Planning Guide Draft and Studies, 1980-1984 (Box 33, Folder 2)
  - Washington National Airport: Utilization and Future of Major Airports in the National Capital Region, Part 2: Stretch Jets, May 19, 1970 (Box 33, Folder 3)
    Senate Hearings
  - Washington National and Dulles International Airport Forecasts, February 1969; November 1971 (Box 33, Folder 4)
  - Washington National and Dulles International Airport Forecasts and Related Materials, September 1974; 1973-1976 (Box 33, Folder 5)
  - Washington National and Dulles International Airports: Comments by Virginians for Dulles and Local Climate Data, 1970-1971 (Box 33, Folder 6)
- Series 5: Newsclippings and Magazines, 1967-1983; (2 boxes)
  This series contains newspaper articles along with a few magazines and pamphlets pertaining to airport problems and policies, especially Washington National Airport and its impact on the community. Most of the Newsclippings come from the Washington Post, but the series also includes clippings from the New York Times, the Northern Virginia Sun, and the Potomac Current. Other newsclippings gathered by Virginians for Dulles can be found in Series 1: Subject Files, some of which were included with correspondence between VFD board members and their lawyers.
  - Magazine Articles, 1968-1971 (Box 33, Folder 7)
    Environmental Science and Technology, Space/Aeronautics, Aviation Week and Space Technology, Business Week, and the Washingtonian
  - Miscellaneous Airline Brochures and Maps: American, northwest, United, 1971-1972 (Box 33, Folder 8)
  - Newsclippings on Concorde and Comments by Virginians for Dulles, 1975-1976 (Box 34, Folder 1)
  - Newsclippings on Noise Pollution and Environmental Impact at Washington National, 1974 (Box 34, Folder 2)
  - Newsclippings on Washington National Airport and General Airport Issues, 1967-1970 (Box 34, Folder 3)
  - Newsclippings on Washington National Airport and General Airport Issues, 1970-1972 (Box 34, Folder 4)
  - Newsclippings on Washington National Airport and General Airport Issues, 1973 (Box 34, Folder 5)
  - Newsclippings on Washington National Airport and General Airport Issues, 1976-1977 (Box 34, Folder 6)
  - Newsclippings on Washington National Airport and General Airport Issues, 1978-1979 (Box 34, Folder 7)
  - Newsclippings on Washington National Airport and General Airport Issues, 1980-1981 (Box 34, Folder 8)
  - Newsclippings on Washington National Airport and General Airport Issues, 1982-1983 (Box 35, Folder 1)
  - Newsclippings on Washington National Airport and General Airport Issues, 1983 (Box 35, Folder 2)
  - Television Transcript: "Washington's Airports: A New Approach" on WDVM-TV, April 20, 1981 (Box 35, Folder 3)
  - Washington Post Business and Finance, June 22, 1967; January 5, 1970 (Box 35, Folder 4)
- Series 6: Audiotapes, 1972; (0.5 box)
  This series contains 6 reel-to-reel tapes. One is a 7 1/2 IPS NASA Special Report from April-May 1972, titled "Jet Noise!... What's Being Done About It?" Two are 1 7/8 IPS tapes dated June 6, 1972 and labeled Dr. Custer and Dr. Gordon. The other three tapes are unlabeled.
  - Dr. Custer (tape 1), June 6, 1972 (Box 35, Reel 1)
  - Side A: Dr. Custer (tape 2); Side B: Dr. Gordon, June 6, 1972 (Box 35, Reel 2)
  - Jet Noise!... What's Being Done About It?, April-May 1972 (Box 35, Reel 3)
    NASA Special Report 85
  - Untitled, undated (Box 35, Reel 4-6)
- Series 7: Oversize, 1968; (1 box)
  This series contains oversize airport plans.
  - Master Plan Report: Washington National Airport, October 1968 (Box 36, Folder 1)
    Federal Aviation Administration; Vincent G. Kling and Associates - Architects
  - Site Plan Scenarios, undated (Box 36, Folder 2)
    Facsimilies